What is the most important question that one should ask about Cedric?
Well, I can tell you the... I don't know whether it's the most important, but it's
the one that gets asked...
I get asked most frequently, which is whether Cedric wanted to build or not.
And the sort of urban myth is that no, he wasn't really interested in building,
because so much of the work is unrealised.
And I would completely dispute that.
I think he absolutely wanted to build.
But if you read through the stories of every single project
and what goes on around every project,
in every case, for very many different reasons in each instance,
Cedric has a very good reason not to complete the project
or the project is abandoned for one reason or another.
So I think those two things get conflated and it's presumed that he never wanted to
build and I think that's wrong.
So I'm always glad that question is asked and I think it's an important one to get
right.
He opened my eyes and this refers back to the experience of understanding what I was
doing could be described as architecture, what I was thinking.
and so he was the opportunity for me to see the architecture was more than a
formal and exercises in formal rearrangement which is what I had
learnt in school and through studying history of art you know history of art
was studied through kind of sequence of styles and as far as I could see it
rearrangement of the same formal components. And learning about Cedric's work I
understood
that it was conceivable, it could be an entirely different construct, which for him
involved
time and speed and fundamentally human, but it was human-centric as opposed to
form-centric
and that was really interesting to me.
Always incredibly enthusiastic,
generous, funny,
really hard work,
incredibly...
Obtuse is the wrong word.
Just fantastically good at taking conversations at a diversion,
which I'm sure lots of people will remark on.
But his personality, certainly from my experience, was incredibly...
..listened intently to what you had to say and always had some response,
although the response was never quite...
It certainly was never what you expected
and never quite registered what he was saying at the time,
but then quite often, years later, you think,
''Oh, that's what that was about.''
I was working in the office,
using the office as a place to work,
In 2000, year 2000, I'd visited it before when as a student, again Cedric was always
very generous about saying, you know, if you want to come and discuss your work, the
office closed at three o'clock.
And after three o'clock you could make an appointment and come up to the office.
So I visited once as a student and after three o'clock all meetings took place in
the white room at the top.
And that meant there was no telephone or no interruption.
And during that meeting, again, I don't remember the specifics of the conversation,
but it was just such a...
As a student, I suppose it was an enormous indulgence in one way.
and he liked to indulge it and he wanted to have the conversation about the work.
So it was, and it was a really good, in a way it was a test as a student.
You know, you had to go and present your work.
It wasn't for a job, it wasn't in a school context.
It was just to talk about your work.
So that was a really unique thing.
Then afterwards, from 2000, when I proposed to make a book of his work, following on
from the
square book that the AA had produced in 1984, which documented the first 20 years of
the office,
that seemed to go out of print and I approached Cedric and said, we need to do, well
one, could
we look at reprinting that and two, could we look at documenting the rest of the
work and he
immediately said no he wasn't interested books take too long they're like
buildings but it's out of date before you've even finished it and it's a
pointless activity so I went away and thought that's a bit mean so and then I went
back
about a month later I said that's really mean and he said well give me a good
reason why you should do it and I said well because the drawers are full of
drawings and projects which should be seen and the only point of doing all of
this stuff is so other people can look at it, particularly students. I reckon
they've
got a lot to learn from what you've been up to. So he relented and immediately
opened
the drawer of his desk and he had a full layout of chapter headings and so he's
clearly been
thinking about it actually. And that was Cedric actually in so many ways. Cedric's
often described
as just a series or a crescendo of paradoxes in every way.
Again, you know, from his appearance to his, also the way he operated,
his appearance being extremely, on the one hand, very formal
and almost sort of Edwardian gent, but at the same time quite moddish.
And he was written about in the US newspapers in the 60s
as being this kind of mod Englishman.
So he always was...
He was playing with that, absolutely,
and absolutely in control of what was going on there.
And also in terms of the way he operated.
He kept every...
Again, from where I...
My understanding, and also having looked now at his diaries,
at the office diaries, and the way that they were laid out,
he kept every part of his life discreet from the other part.
So his private life was very private.
What happened between seven and nine in the morning
was a particular sequence of conversations with a particular set of people,
which then had no overlap with office hours of what occurred in the office.
Lunchtime then was also used for different kinds of meetings with clients,
or mostly clients actually.
and then the afternoon then goes into another sort of area of research or other
interests
or you know sort of peripheral activities which all culminated in projects one way
or
another. But they're very very discrete and therefore kept people very separate. And
similarly
with the situation of the contents coming out of the drawer, you know, he was always
working on one level or another. That's what Cedric did from, I guess, five in the
morning
till two o'clock the following morning. I don't think he slept very much.
Physically,
it was separated. You know, he had his office on the, his desk on the first floor
and then
the white room was this completely other space, which the office members, I mean,
when, if
you speak to them, they'll, they were rarely invited except if it was a party or a
particular
event but not in the day-to-day running that was absolutely where guests came
and on Saturday mornings he would have special sessions to discuss a project
and invite people up so everything was very very clearly organized in his mind
and in his diary and in that in that para and the paradox I guess lies in the
fact that the what he was constantly doing the work always but always gave
the appearance of being entirely spontaneous and never quite, and always questioning
and
doubt being kind of fundamental to his philosophy. So that questioning I think often
gave the
impression that he really wasn't particularly organised or knowing what was going on
there,
but it was completely the opposite.
Well I think delight again it comes back to this sort of human centric idea of what
architecture
was useful for. It was potentially it was useful as a source of human delight or it
should be, that's what its role should be and why shouldn't it be. And I think that
specifically in architecture that's something he tried to build in to what he
designed.
There was always a, really often in most projects, there was such comical aspects to
the, one,
the fact that often they were either dynamic, literally dynamic buildings, or the
way he
thought about details in terms of entry or exit, or there were always, he was always
making observations about how that could be uplifting as a moment in engaging with
architecture
opposed to something just practically functional or utilitarian. Although
aesthetically that's
often how they come across so I think again sometimes it gets lost but certainly in
terms
of the architecture that's there in all of the drawings and always the fact that he
peoples his
drawings in the projects. People are always doing funny things looking or you know
they're
They're incredibly tender in the way that they're drawn.
So there's delight in that respect.
And then just delight in his general well-being.
He was extremely ebullient.
So I think that's a word, a way of describing,
as a character, you know, an amazing laugh.
Well, I think the one that really,
Fun Palace, I think, has to be.
I mean, it was more or less the first.
It wasn't chronologically the first,
but it was very early on in his career.
And it set the tone and set the agenda
for so many aspects of all the projects that came after.
And various parts of that project were then developed through generators,
absolutely a by-product of Fun Palace, the Oxford Corner Houses,
magnet right at the end is also in lots of ways.
So I think all roads do lead to Fun Palace really
in terms of its significance
and just the sheer size of the project
in terms of numbers of people involved,
aspects that he tried to engage in
in terms of the hardware of the building and the software,
the whole establishing of the cybernetics committee
and in terms of thinking about programming.
Fun Palace officially started in 1960.
I think there were conversations occurring a little prior to 1960.
Certainly Cedric and Jane Littlewood were introduced in about 1958 by Tom Dryberg.
The three of them then became the sort of core body that ran the project.
And then it finished in 1966, sort of officially, when they retracted their planning
application from the Millmead site,
which is the site just below what we now know as the Olympic Park.
It's very close to Stratford.
They were looking at a number of different sites over a number of years,
always trying to, really trying to find the place for the Fun Palace.
That was a huge part of the work.
And Millmeads was the closest because it was offered as an opportunity to start to
promote this by the Civic Trust,
who owned that land, that tract of land in East London, which is part of the Lee
Valley.
And so they were very supportive of it.
in the end politically there was a shift there was a change in uh county hall and a
change in
the political makeup of of london and the support and one week it's there the next
week it's not and
it was as simple it was really as simple as that and there was a a challenge to the
to the fun
palace um that the site that it was going to be built on was very close to
stormwater tanks
which would deal with flooding and also sewage outflow.
So it lost out to the sewage outflow tanks.
And Cedric and Joan of Lourdes quite rightly decided
that sewage outflow was more important than Fun Palace
for Londoners, actually, which I think is big of them.
The Maccabee Project.
That was commissioned by Sir Alistair McAlpine, who was a friend of Cedric's.
And about ten years Cedric's junior, someone described him as Cedric's...
That Cedric had created the perfect client.
I think McAlpine was a very, he was an interesting man because he left school very
young, he was a total autodidact, went straight into the family business I think at
the age of about 15 or 16, working on the construction site and worked his way up to
the office.
He was very adamant to his, all his uncles and father were working in the offices at
an administrative level.
And he insisted he wanted to know the business from the construction site.
So he was interesting in that respect, I think, to Cedric.
And also on the part that he was part of this family, very large family construction
company.
When the project happened in the 70s, it was at the time where the labour force was
still very much unreconstructed.
It was completely unregulated.
So a lot of the labourers were Irish labourers coming over, being paid cash in hand.
conditions were terrible and deaths on sites were just astronomical I mean they were
in there
hundreds of thousands people would die on construction sites all over the country so
there's this very in the project files etc there's this great statistic and I
haven't got the numbers
on the tip of my tongue but there was this statistic of how many deaths in the year
that
project started had occurred in construction so that was really the for him I think
the catalyst
for the project and then the other catalyst being that there were a number of sites
under
construction that McAlpines were responsible for and they were looking to make their
business
more efficient. How could they save money and make money and Cedric saw it very much
that
it was a logistical exercise in many ways how to organize the construction sites so
one it became
a safer place to work but also how it could become a more efficient place it was a
specific case of
of how to have a crane on site and not have to remove it and bring it back but how
you could
keep the crane on the site conducting a number of different maneuvers and not have
to go through
logistics of so in lots of ways extremely simple in the one hand perhaps
totally unrelated to architecture or the final product of architecture but
entirely related to the process of making architecture and again from the
human perspective in terms of how you make that both healthier and happier
mentally, physically and economically for everybody. So that was the impetus for
the project. It's very hard because I have lots actually but I think one of
one of my favorite drawings is for a project called Tertlan which is in
in Groszny in Croatia. And it was one workshop Cedric did in the early 90s for a
small hill
town. And he, the premise for the project was to, he did it in a week, so it's a set
of three or four drawings. But it was to, how to bring this very ancient hill town
into
the 21st century. This is, as I said, very early 90s, so pre-broadband and internet
connection,
although of course the notions were already very present. So Cedric designs this
halo,
a physical halo around the village which is held up by three lifting cranes. And
then
With the advent of broadband coming in, I'm imagining he thinks it could just be
driven
away or if you no longer decide you want to be linked to the rest of the world, it
could
be removed.
But it was just such a...
There are two just beautiful pencil drawings of that project which are extremely...
He drew all the time and he drew what he saw and he drew the landscape a lot and
with very
few lines in the kind of greatest sense of a cartoonist actually, with the skill of
a
cartoonist who doesn't need many lines to communicate a huge amount of information,
he could do that with landscape and architectural drawing which I think no one else
has got
close to. How are we to understand Cedric as an enabler or the use of architecture
as an enabler?
I think Cedric saw it very much in terms of, well he stated it that I think he saw
it very
much in terms of the progression of technology and he saw the progression of
technology was
was smaller, faster, lighter. And that that was about, information technology was
going
to be the technology that drove humanity from where he was leaving off pretty well.
And
therefore human beings were going to be making more decisions for themselves. And in
that
respect he then saw that as a way of
what about, how does that, what are the
consequences for architecture then? If human beings, individuals
will make increasingly more and more decisions for themselves, they will not come
from some other governing body.
And so he tried to design with that
in mind and that meant always a level of interaction
between the user of a building and the artefact itself,
or the building itself,
which allowed the user to determine the use also.
So in the example of Generator, for instance,
which was a perfect demonstration of that idea,
the buildings could be physically moved,
it could be planned and physically moved around the site
by the users according to their desires.
And you would never, one could never predetermine that
until it was actually used.
You would never know what the outcome of that building would be
until you started as a user to use it.
So I think he saw architecture as an enabler in that respect,
and as the architect, you then supplied enough kit
for that to happen, to begin.
I think the relevance of Cedric Price today
is that he had this idea about human,
more decision-making being made by individuals increasingly
and how one does that or learns to handle that.
I think that's the most useful thing that Cedric talked about.
and was interested in.
And then what the consequences of architecture can do
in relation to that.
But his fascination in human beings, I think,
is what is relevant about Cedric,
and I think what the industry has a huge amount still to learn.
And one can learn it by reading his writing.
It just is hard work.
He was so cryptic in so many ways that you have to work twice as hard as he did
and he worked really, really hard.
Really hard.
The archive is testament to the amount of work he did
and the amount of work he...
what he demanded from his clients
and the people that worked for him and with him
and his readers.
When you read, he demands that you pay attention
and also that you think for yourself and you take from...
Same with the drawings. Drawings and the text.
You take what's useful for you and then you go with it.
He doesn't want you to copy it or...
You have to use it to think for yourself.